this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers take your marks it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
enter systems iris it's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible it's time to
use any data from any source it's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform
the fastest way to build applications
ready set code start coding for free
visit inner systems.com slash tried to
try iris hello everyone this is Felina
for so for engineering radio today with
me on the show I have Carl use he is a
CTO at great network and he helps to
make technology speakers succeed at CFB
lend welcome to the show Carl yeah
thanks for having me Felina so the topic
of today's show is public speaking and
you actually wrote a book on how to get
started with public speaking and that's
what this episode will cover I would
like to know first
why should engineers be good at public
speaking I mean they're already good at
engineering so what are the reasons for
people that they might be interested in
improving their public speaking skills
well I think that is kind of a personal
decision it comes down to what your
goals are as an engineer or as in your
career in general so for me personally
what it came down to was kind of
necessity I started to move from
individual contributor to team lead and
then a manager a few years ago and as I
did that I realized that a lot more of
my day-to-day job was getting up in
front of people and either presenting
is that I gathered from the team or
maybe presenting progress project and
then facilitating conversations and all
this stuff that ended up being a lot
more about the people and the
conversations and the speaking than it
was about the sort of writing covered
all day and so for me it was that that
movement into management kind of pushed
me to start learning to become a better
public speaker I've met plenty of other
engineers throughout the course of
writing the the public speaking guide I
talked to about 35 conference speakers
technical conference speakers and they
have a wide variety of reasons for
wanting to get public speaking some of
them do that do it as part of their job
so there's a whole field that I had
never even heard of before I started
researching for this book called
developer advocacy or developer
relations and these are technical
developers who also go up in front of
audiences at conferences and meetups and
either promote a product or sort of show
off an open-source tool so if you've
been to many tech conferences you've
probably seen someone from Twilio or
auth0 speaking and that's because they
have whole teams that do this there's
also people who do this to promote their
side projects so I know a lot of
developer just have open source work
that they want to kind of make sure how
that people hear about and a great way
to do that is to go to meetups or
conferences and speak so there's a again
like a wide range of reasons that people
get into public speaking it's hard to
classify just a few of them but I did
come spend some time looking through and
cataloging some of the most common ones
and those kind of hit the top of the
list there and then your personal reason
was actually not so much about public
speaking if I summarized that correctly
it was more about getting better at
communicating in general and you found
that public speaking was a good way to
practice how to explain your thoughts to
people yeah that's right so one thing
I've found is that when you're giving a
talk it would say even a Lunch and Learn
or a meetup or a conference you have to
take a lot of information that's in a
variety of different sources and
organize and distill it into something
that people can comprehend in 45 minutes
or less maybe and that's a really
challenging communication skill it's
it's beyond just the act of getting up
and saying some words on I guess on the
stage it's also organ
and it's the ability to understand who
your audience is and where they're at
currently at this point in time
so public speaking is really a lot
broader than just a physical act of
standing up in front of people in same
words it's also about all those other
things that happen behind the scenes
which I find really interesting and
maybe surprising as I started to speak
more in either business context or
professional contents oh yeah I like the
perspective about how creating a talk is
also about how to gather information and
organize it that we will definitely get
back to that later in the show but first
I would like to ask you to take people
through the process of a conference
organization how do conferences find
people and how do you get in as a
speaker into that process this is
something also you're covering the book
quite extensively
yeah so the book is directed at people
who want to start giving technical talks
at conferences so mostly these are
software engineers or managers or even
developer relations people who just want
to get on on stage and start you know
presenting what they know for whatever
is it and so a big part of that
that new speakers have to overcome is
what do I do to actually physically get
on stage like what are the steps you
have to take before that point and
there's actually quite a bit that goes
into it so when you're organizing a
conference and I've never organized a
conference personally I've been running
a meetup group for a little over a year
now in Chicago but when you organize a
conference one of the big parts of it is
you have to find speakers so conferences
do this in a number of different ways
some conferences as they get more
selective or larger they might just only
handpick speakers but the broad majority
of tech conferences today especially the
community-run ones and the ones that you
might find in you know smaller regions
they open up what's called a CFP or a
call for proposals some people also call
a call for papers that kind of comes
from academia and what happens there is
you open the conference organizers will
open up a call for proposals for let's
say two or three months they'll take a
bunch of proposals from speakers who
potentially want to talk and then
they'll pick the top however many date
they have slots for so some conferences
they may pick dozens of speakers I've
been to have been a speaker at code man
before and it's a huge regional
conference in the Midwest and they had I
want to say over a hundred speakers so
it was huge then there are smaller
conferences so I also asked last year
spoke at a conference and here in
Chicago if it had a single track and it
was about 200 maybe 250 attendees and
for them they only had 8 speakers or 10
speakers I think and so it can vary
quite a bit how many speakers actually
get chosen but either way they'll open
up to the cfb process and anyone who's
interested can apply now one of the big
challenges you have to find those CFPs
that are open so if you're speaking
there's a number of ways you can do that
CFP land is just one of the many sites
that tracks CFPs that are open so
there's a lot of great places out there
and eventually you'll start to build
your own list once the speaker's have
all applied at the CFP is closed the
conference organizers will then go
through some process to figure out who's
the best person to talk at their event
now there's a lot of different ways that
they actually make the selection in
general the conference's will put some
idea of what they want speakers to talk
about up front in the application so
they'll say something like you know
we're doing a react conference we want
you to submit talks about building
production level scale of apps in react
and maybe there's two or three other
things that they want to highlight and
generally the speakers who have sort of
have talks in that vein will probably
get selected first now that's not always
true they always are gonna try to pick
some variety and so they may pick some
talks that are well you might call soft
talk which is maybe more about managing
teams with react or how react solves
business problems or things like that
because those are tangentially related
to the sort of core of the conference
but also really important for people to
hear about and the way that conferences
actually then pick you know which of
these talks are best at that varies as
well so some will do a public voting
system where they'll open it up to
either former attendees of the
conference or maybe just people in their
community and say you know which of
these talks would you most like to see
and they'll just let the ones with the
most votes win some will just review
talks as they come in they may have like
a organizing committee that is in charge
of reviewing all the talks and thinking
picking the best ones as they come in
and then some of them will not tell you
anything about it it's got a secretive
process and maybe it's just one person
who picks all up and picks every talk so
again it convert vary quite a bit and
you don't always know is speaker but
sometimes they'll give you a little bit
of insight into it and so that's kind of
a rough overview of the process I don't
know if I missed anything there I know
that there's kind of a lot to cover like
you said and a little more than the
guide but I'm happy to dive into the
specifics if you want to yeah at least
this gives people some idea of what's
going on behind the scenes and then of
course a question is imagine I found a
call for proposals of a conference I
sort of like let's say it's about Python
and I do Python programming and how do I
know this conference will fit because
there might be dozens of conferences
about Python and they might differ in
scale and level what is your strategy
for selecting the right conference to
apply to yeah so you mentioned the topic
area is important that's definitely the
first criteria if you're a speaker and
you want to speak about Python you you
probably don't want to go submit to a
bunch of Ruby conferences you're not
likely to get picked and your talks are
just not gonna be appropriate so it's
got to have the right topic area the
second thing you want to look at is is
this the right location or is this a
location I can realistically get to so
if there's one conference that happens
in Antarctica every year and if you if
they aren't covering the cost of travel
that is a huge huge plane ride to get
down there so I think it's actually
claimed several plane rides and maybe a
boat or something at the end so think
about the location know that it's
somewhere you could realistically get to
and what's interesting there is that a
lot of conferences is not well it's
probably about 50% of conferences will
help speakers cover some of their travel
costs for a lot of other conferences
they maybe don't have the budget to do
that so you may want to talk to your
employer about who they cover it if
you've got accepted so location is a big
part and then next is the the financial
viability of you going so again if that
conference is not going to cover any of
your travel or hotel costs are you gonna
be able to take those out of pocket I've
actually gone to a spoken at a couple
conferences where they didn't cover the
hotel but I had a friend in town and so
I just stayed with my friend and it's
maybe not as glamorous as staying in the
hotel for the conference itself or not
as easy because I had to do a little
travel but I did get to see somebody who
I haven't seen in a while so it's it's
kind of fun to do that too once you get
in to speaking regularly
you're gonna start thinking a little
more about some other criteria like you
said there are a lot of conferences at
CFP LAN we index well over four or five
hundred tech conferences every year and
I know there are more that I don't even
you know I don't know about so a big
part of what experienced speakers look
for is reputation so I'm in a speaker's
slack group for example that whenever a
new CFP or new conference comes on
online a lot of the speakers will go in
and ask other speakers you know as
anybody been to this one or applied to
this one what's what is it like there
they take care of their speakers is it
are they thinking about things like
diversity and inclusion are they
reputable organization is it for-profit
not-for-profit there's a lot of things
there that you can dig into now when you
are early on speaking it's maybe your
first couple conferences you may not you
may not consider everything like that
you may just take whatever you can get
but at some point you're gonna want to
become a little more selective in your
choices yeah that makes sense this goes
for a lot of things in life I guess so
imagine you have found a conference that
you think oh this fits and it's in a
location that I would like now what so I
know some stuff about let's say Python
again how do I know what of everything
of a programming language or a framework
what specific part could be interesting
for that conference yeah so when they
when you you sort of pick out some CFPs
or conferences that you want submit to
you're gonna go find their CFP page and
you're gonna see you know when is the
when's it due you're gonna see do they
cover travel and hotel and they're
probably also going to include some tips
for submitting your CFP so it might be
stuff like at this Python conference we
are gonna focus on machine learning
topics and so if that's the case you
want to think about what topics do you
already know about or have already
spoken about that we've matched that
criteria now this is kind of like I'm
sort of jumping the gun
a bit here because assuming you have
some knowledge about let's say a topic
like Python you also need to decide what
are you actually going to speak about
and usually speakers will start by
having two or three abstracts that
they've written or and I'll get into
abstracts in a second but they'll have
two or three abstracts they've written
and they'll look for conferences that
are good fits to submit them and so you
may find that there's 20 Python
conferences happening in the next few
months but only four or five of them are
really good fits for one of the talks
that you've already got in you know
ready to give and so you may only submit
to those or you may try a couple others
that are sort of a okay fit or something
like that you never know you may make it
in anyway
now abstracts is kind of a mentioned
that but I didn't explain what that is
so I'll back up here when a conference
opens its call for proposals they will
ask you to submit a talk title an
abstract and maybe some other supporting
information or documents the title is
just a you know catchy like quick way to
refer to your talk and there's sort of a
whole there's a little art to writing
good titles for talks I want to have
been to quite yet and then the abstract
is usually a one one or two paragraph
kind of what is the talk and sometimes
that abstract will go directly into the
conference's program so you want to
think about who's the audience it's
going to be reading this abstract it's
going to be the organizers who are
making the conference but ultimately
it's gonna be the developers and
attendees at the conference itself so
you need to think how could I write this
a description of my talk that's super
compelling for that audience once you've
got your abstract written they may also
ask you for some things like have you
given talks like this before then they
ask to see a video so you may put a link
in they may ask for links to your social
media accounts because to be perfectly
honest a lot of conferences are looking
for speakers that have some presence
online or at least a you know something
out there that they can kind of event
that you're reliable that you're going
to show up you're not going to get on
stage and lock up or get really scared
so this kind of you know sort of go what
works back a little bit here but what a
lot of speakers will do is they'll try
to
their talks at meetup group a local
meetup group or a user group in their
area before they start submitting to
conferences and that can really help
because you can get it recorded you can
kind of get some feedback from the
audience you can understand a little
better how this topic is really going to
resonate with people in my target
audience before you actually get into
submitting it to conferences also helps
build some credibility and some
confidence in public speaking so I've
talked a bit about youyou the conference
is gonna open up the CFP you're gonna
submit an abstract and you're gonna want
to think about you know whether it fits
for the conference is a topic that you
actually care about and you're excited
about giving a talk on you know when I
interviewed all the the conference
speakers for the the book the big thing
that came across and a large majority of
them was that they really cared about
the topics they talked about and it's
funny because you know I may not get
super excited about I don't know Q's and
Redis or something but there's somebody
out there who does and there's somebody
out there who knows a ton about it and
can give talks on it and they probably
really like that topic really interested
in fascinated by the technical
intricacies there so find something that
is actually exciting for you because at
the end of the day you're gonna spend a
lot of time thinking about learning
about this topic and if you're not
excited about it it's gonna come across
in your your talk next you want to think
like is this something is this a talk
that topic that I actually know pretty
well but one great way to come up with
talk ideas is to think about your last
several big projects you've worked on at
work now there's some sometimes you have
to be careful about what you say about
your work up on stage because they may
or may not be there may or may not be
privacy or security concerns so you'll
have to clear all this with your boss
and sometimes legal groups but depends
on the company work for either way if
you've worked on a project so for
example a friend of mine was trying to
come up with a talk idea he kept saying
I don't know I've worked on anything
really that unique and I asked you know
what are the last two or three projects
you've done and he mentioned
internationalizing an app and I was like
that's awesome I've worked at a software
engineer for almost 10 years and I've
never had to deal with
internationalization and it's like he
didn't even realize that that was
something
that a lot of us probably never had to
do especially if we worked in my small
niche us markets and things like that
and so it's really interesting once you
start running some of your projects by
your friends you'll start to hear oh
I've never done that that would be
interesting so those are some good ways
to come up with talk ideas and then from
there once you've written your abstract
you can start submitting that to
conferences and then usually usually
conference speakers will actually have
their abstract ready long before they
have their slides in presentation so
maybe we'll get two slides and
presentation a bit but that kind of
gives you an idea about how you submit
that abstract and how you actually pick
a good topic I really like that advice
I'm gonna summarize it briefly I think
your main takeaway for selecting a topic
was look at what you've done in the past
few months or years and then bounce
ideas off of friends program all the
programmers that you know and then if
you have a vaguely defined idea find a
meet-up or a lunch and learn and work
and then practice the talk there so just
- you have video and you have an idea of
what the talk will be about and then if
you've done that that would be a good
time to submit your abstracts to qohor
proposals right yeah that's fantastic
this is a great summary so now let's get
to talk selection imagine you have this
nice abstract now what what do we know
about reasons that speakers get selected
or do not get selected at conferences
what are some tips that you could give
us to write a good abstracts to actually
get in to the conference yeah it's
really hard to know exactly because most
conferences are organized by a group of
people and usually that they'll try to
get a somewhat diverse knowledgeable
group of people at different skill
levels to review all of the abstracts
that get submitted and they're looking
for a few things and it's hard to know
in what proportion they're looking for
each thing so one is they want to see
that your your topic and abstract are
well thought out and unique and that
they are compelling and so it sounds
like something you could get excited
about the next thing they might be
looking at is do we have a good blend of
topics so for example if I submit a talk
about let's say using laravel a PHP
framework or something
and I submit that to a PHP conference
but then the organizer of laravel
submits the talk about his his framework
that the guy who created when Bela
submits to talk about his framework as
well then I am not gonna get accepted
because they're gonna want a blend of
topics and it's unlikely that they'll
pick you know me over the person who is
the creator of the framework another
thing that comes into play is the
speaker's reputation so every time you
go I guess I conference speaking while
there's you know hundreds of events it's
actually a pretty small world I found
that a lot of conference speakers get to
know each other and a lot of organizers
are also speakers so they get to know
other speakers organizers and it ends up
becoming like there's a lot of
reputation that gets passed around so
you can do a lot to build your
reputation that is not even speaking one
one thing you can do is contribute to or
work on open source projects you could
start speaking again at meetups
or maybe local boot camps that's been a
really helpful way for me to kind of get
up on stage a little bit and you'll
start to develop as you you know go to
these things you'll meet people you'll
develop a bit of a reputation as a
speaker and then it gets easier to get
accepted at conferences as well because
they've heard your name around there's
also are you actually qualified on this
topic and I don't want to turn beginners
off because actually a lot of
conferences now are also looking
explicitly for people who are in the
first five years their career to give
talks because they want a diversity of
skill ranges but a lot of technical
conferences are looking for people who
are really well qualified on the topic
so if you have been working in let's say
Java for ten years you've got a better
shot getting accepted at giving an
advanced Java talk at a conference than
if you just started last year and that's
gonna show up on your either LinkedIn or
your Twitter or whatever you do it and
then like I kind of touched on in the
last point a lot of conferences are
starting to look at how can we get a
diverse pool of speakers and diversity
doesn't just mean you know the skin
color and gender it also means like are
we getting people who are new to the
topic so if you think about it
conference attendees
and they have a wide range of experience
levels so it's great if you have
speakers who also have a wide range of
experience levels and you then want to
kind of do the job the organizers will
do the job matching up the beginner
talks with the beginner attendees and
the advanced talks the advanced
attendees and I think that's really
great it's awesome to get this blending
of different skill levels because while
I may be a senior I don't know PHP
developer I may be a junior rails
developer and so I may want to go to
those kinds of beginner talks even
though I'm a senior person some other
topic there's no you know we're all
beginners at something once the comments
is kind of like started to narrow down
their talks some of it becomes
logistical so they've got to find
speakers who are still available so they
may send out a you know hey we've
accepted you to speak but you may or may
not actually be able to speak because
maybe you committed to something else or
a family event came up and so that
that's a whole kind of a whole nother
topic but that gives you a little idea
and how what conferences are looking to
do as they fill out their schedule of
speakers for a bit so this is a tough
question because I'm not sure what my
own opinion on this is but is it okay as
a speaker or maybe even as a beginning
speaker to reach out to conference
organizers around or outside of the call
for proposals is this a total logo or is
this actually a smart way to get some
information on what the conference might
be interested in yeah I don't think it's
a bad idea I think it's going to I'll
just warn you and say it's gonna be
tough to get much face time or much
phone time with conference organizers I
found that a lot of the conference
organizers are very busy people and even
in the offseason when you know it's not
time to their conference they either
have a full-time job they work at or
they may do other kinds of event
marketing for other you know for their
company so it's not a bad idea if you
get the chance to talk to an organizer
let's say that you know you really want
to go talk at angularjs comp and you
meet somebody who's in charge of running
it it may be great to you know sit down
have a 30-minute conversation with them
but it also may be really hard to do
because they might be really busy
another way you could sort of tackle
this same that same problem of like I
want to know
about the conference before I commit to
speaking or before I submit you could
talk to former speakers at that
conference they might be a little more
available one thing I found talking to
conference speakers is that they are
generally very helpful people that want
to make the world a better place and
they want to lift other speakers up
which is really great it's an awesome
community to be part of so what I might
encourage you to do if you're a new
speaker and you want to learn more about
it is maybe find two or three people in
your city who have spoken at conferences
before or even come up to someone who
speaks at a conference that you go to
and ask them hey could we go in coffee
sometime I'd love to just hear more
about the process of getting accepted
here at these specific conferences I
think you're very likely to get time
with them on the books that is really a
lovely idea and I just want to say if
people want to reach out to me to talk
about conference speaking I would be
totally open to be as well well that's
lovely
okay so I think we've covered getting
into conferences enough now I want to
get into actually doing the presentation
because previously you already mentioned
when you submit an abstract you just
submit it silent abstract you don't have
to have your slides in your presentation
all finish and I think you know honesty
most speakers actually do not have their
slides entirely finished until unless
it's maybe like a recap of a talk
they've already done so okay my talk is
except it's now what will happen what do
i do oh girl yeah exactly it and that's
a you're totally right most of the
speakers I interviewed for this this
whole guide was where we're in that same
boat they would write maybe three or
four abstracts the beginning of the year
they would start submitting them to
conferences and just see which ones got
accepted then as one got accepted they'd
figure out how to make the slides and
all that now if you're a first-time
speaker it might be a good idea to have
given the talk because it's gonna be a
good practice but once you get into this
you can sort of start to think about you
know I know the topic pretty well I
could write an outline so I can probably
come up with a presentation here so once
you get accepted and assuming that the
timing works out and you can go and they
want you to go and you can pay for it
all of that stuff you know which there's
a lot to that but that that happens
first now you've got to think about okay
what does my presentation for this
there's a lot of ways you can do this I
like to break this down into four sort
of core formats that people use for
talks now this is not exhaustive there's
probably lots of other variations on
each of these but just to help you
categorize things the first format that
I see a lot is a novel solution to a
common problem so this is like where you
know someone at a big company let's say
Google has some really weird or I'm
sorry it has a very common problem but
they have this unique spin on it because
they're big enough they're Google they
come up and build their own tool for it
so I kinda I think that that's how
Google got into kubernetes was
essentially like they're running lots of
doctor containers they realize that it's
not quite working they they kind of come
up with this really novel solution for
it and there's a lot of people who go
talk about kubernetes from google
because of that relationship and that
project that may be a bad example I
don't know a ton about the internals of
you know Google and how they came up
with that but that's a really a good
format because what it's letting you do
is sort of lots of people have this
common problem now your solution is
specific to you but at least they're
gonna start thinking in terms of okay
that's how they solved it maybe I can
solve it kind of similarly another topic
that I've seen done this way is like
there was a lot of micro services have
kind of been on the rise and then on the
less sort of more stable side of things
anyway they were really cool a few years
ago a lot of people were talking about
them and there's lots of common problems
that come up once you start building in
micro services so there's how do you
deal with communication and dropping
connections between services how do you
deal with lungeing data between multiple
services and lots of people came up with
different novel solutions for this and
have great conference talks around it so
that's another way you can sort of
structure a talk another common way of
structuring talks and this is kind of
goes beyond technical talks but is
called the hero's journey so this is a
pattern for storytelling and the way I
break it down I kind of make a
simplified version in the guide but
first of all you introduce yourself in
some kind of happy initial state
everything's working well at your job
everything's going great and the code is
getting deployed working all the time
and then something happens that upsets
your initial state maybe
all of a sudden it's really hard to
track down bug nobody can figure it out
and it's come to you to fix it and then
you reluctantly start your journey to
resolve that conflict so you say all
right what are the things I can try you
start trying things you you sort of walk
through all the different things you try
to kind of maybe bring the audience in
to suggest things and all that and then
you reach sort of a low point where your
initial assumptions and everything
you've tried has failed
and you're really having a hard time and
then maybe something something finally
clicks and whether that's because maybe
a co-worker came in and helped you out
or it's a book you read that finally
unlocked it or you just went and took a
long walk and all the sudden you realize
what the problem was you were trying to
solve how you could do that and you
emerge victorious is kind of the way
that the hero's journey ends and this is
like the pattern that every every action
movies or follows so it's not a bad idea
to make that part of your your
conference talk it's a great way to give
yourself some framework here another
framework that people use is the
tech-heavy deep dive so this is
something where you go into a really
really niche problem so instead go for a
common problem in your novel solution
you go to a really weird novel problem
that not everyone or very few people
will have and then you get really
technical with solving it so these are
those low-level talks that get into like
memory management in some kind of
assembly language and stuff like that
which I find super interesting because I
am usually in my day to day job I'm a
very high-level programmer working in
you know these web languages and so it's
really cool to get back into this deep
tech stuff and a lot of people do a good
job talking like that and if you can
take that really deep technical content
and make it approachable for the broader
audience that's a super powerful skill
to have and the last kind of way to
structure a talk is the live demo live
demos are super impressive and super
challenging and really risky I've seen
them go very very poorly I've also seen
to go really really well so if you can
pull it off great but I would say
there's a lot of ways you can you got to
mitigate your risk but be really careful
get get really good at this practice at
a time it is really hard to develop
take your marks it's time to upgrade
your Data Platform to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex
mission-critical applications in the
fastest route possible it's time to use
any data from any source it's time to
embed analytics and create interactive
user interfaces so what are you waiting
for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform the
fastest way to build applications
ready set code start coding for free
visit inner systems comm / try to try
iris yeah we'll definitely get into life
coding a little bit later in the episode
for now I just want to summarize those
four different story lines that people
could use if they are designing a talk
so one is the hero story one is a life
demo that we will get into one is an
existing problem that people might be
able to relate to but then presenting a
normal solution and in the final format
you talked about was this tech deep dive
that really involves the nitty gritty
details yes so then I definitely help
people to get into a story what actually
what type of presentation am i designing
and that might be even helpful I'm
thinking now not just in creating the
slides but also in writing the abstract
you could have that in mind of what type
of talk is this gonna be so how do I
describe it also so many to make it
clear to the organizers what of which of
the four this one is yes yep absolutely
so how do you learn to create such a
story I have the four now but not one
like what can I do to get better at this
I mean clearly reach your poke but also
what other tips do you have for
practicing yeah I think one is start
watching good conference talks
critically and the great thing is that
we live in an age where like video is on
YouTube almost immediately after every
conference it's it's great like even if
you can't attend afford to attend every
conference which nobody can you can get
online and find videos on almost every
major tech
reference and you can find some of the
keynote speakers or some of the smaller
speakers and you can get a great idea of
what they how they give these talks and
you can decide which parts of their
talks you like and don't like and which
sort of methods say use that you do it
don't like so there's not really a right
answer to this a lot of it comes down to
finding what works for you as a as a
speaker and what what kind of resonates
with your audience so I'll say first
like watch talks because I think that's
a really good way to get ideas about how
you could deliver a talk and what kind
of methods you could use and then the
next thing is start just start giving
talks and practicing a lot and
practicing is the step that I think a
lot of people early on miss and it shows
and when there's a couple ways you can
practice so the first thing you know as
you start to develop a talk you're going
to start to have an outline and maybe
you'll get a few slides
start to actually pretend like you're
actually giving it so book a conference
room and your office and give it in
front of an empty room and see how it
feels see if it's it's actually starting
to flow and make sense you know you're
starting to get some ideas about how
people would actually respond to this
and then as you do that more and you get
more comfortable with that you start to
refine your outline your slides you kind
of get the whole thing going and then
you want to start giving that and
realized and so maybe first give it to a
few co-workers just to try it out but
get a little lunch and learn it's always
nice give it to a local meetup or to
give it to you can you know call up some
area code boot camps and see if they're
interested in having you come give it as
a talk
you could then start applying to
conferences with it and you'll have it
really well refined by the time you
actually get there in front of a larger
audience at the conference I really like
both of those tips definitely practicing
is something that really helps and the
other thing you mentioned was watch
talks critically and that sounds nice
but actually I don't think it's so easy
to actually critically look at talks and
that brings me to another question
actually before the show I asked you
could you give a few of your favorite
talks and what you like about them so
this might
a good time to talk about those two
shows at those two talks that you
mentioned before the show we will link
to those in the show know so you can
look at them and then listen to the rest
of the episode if you don't want it to
be spoiled those thoughts were sandy
Mets on coat smells at Lehrer calm and
Nicholas means about the Three Mile
Island at the Li Deaf conference and I
really like to hear from you what why
did you select those talks what is so
great about them what can people take
away from watching those talks if
they're gonna watch the talks after the
interview yeah I rewatched those talks
this weekend because I it's been a
couple years since I had seen them a lot
I saw both of them live do these and
I've seen these particular two speakers
I've watched a lot of their other talks
because they just both fascinate me and
for different reasons so start with
Sandi Metz she's big presence in the
Ruby community and I'm not a ruby person
but I still think that her talks a lot
of times are very approachable to anyone
she's she's very much a programmers
programmer she really thinks about
programming as a craft and making code
better and that level of that detail
level stuff is really interesting and
kind of fun to watch because a lot of
times I forget that you know there is a
wind up you're trying to always make
things better and it kind of takes me
back out of that in this particular talk
she's talking about code smells which is
a way to sort of identify maybe anti
patterns or problems or potential
problem areas in a code base so it's
great they all have really unique and
funny names and so that's kind of part
of the fun of this talk but she talks at
the beginning about her personal
challenge in understanding and
categorizing code smells and how
challenging that was for her at first
and instead of then like maybe spending
one slide per smell and just going like
you know here's a definition of this
code smell give us a sample
it was definition here's a sample like
she could have done that I think that
would have been too like natural
inclination for a lot of speakers but
instead she sort of grouped them
together and her slides are just an
image that illustrates the smell and
then she just talks
and her ability to explain something in
his natural conversational way it just
shows you she knows this topic really
really really well and I think that it
when that comes across it's really
powerful one thing that I've noticed a
lot of really good speakers do including
Sandy in this talk is they don't include
a lot of text on their slides
they include maybe a keyword or
keyphrase and a big image to sort of
illustrate it but then they just they
speak and they use they know that the
audience can only either watch the
slides and read slides or hear them talk
and internalizing that takes some time I
still have I still struggle with this a
lot of mine talks I feel like how are
still two texts heavy and I'm aware
that's a problem but but it's still
really it's hard to overcome because as
a speaker that you're you're often
thinking well I should want to make sure
they see this this definition and so
therefore I'll put it up there but the
truth is the audience can't do both they
can't read and listen to you at the same
time so she does a great job with that
the other thing that I kind of I take
from this talk is that it's really
inspiring and it's hard to make a talk
that is about such a mechanical topic
code smells inspiring but honestly it
comes off that way it's like you can
make your code better you can take any
codebase and improve it by just applying
these you know smells and common
refactoring patterns that you include
some inner talk so I really like talks
that you walk away from and you go yes I
can be better that can make me you know
I can actually use this and this is
something I can take right tonight it's
very actionable for my day-to-day life
this program on the other hand here
we've got Nick means Nicholas means he
gives a lot of talks that are in this
similar vein as this one it's about what
I think is called who destroyed room and
or who failed at three at Three Mile
Island yeah I don't know I just have the
Three Mile Island as a site I'm gonna
look at it real quick yeah it's called
who destroyed Three Mile Island so okay
Nicholas beans is he's a great
storyteller I got to speak at this
conference the lead developer a couple
years ago and he was one of the keynotes
and this was his talk and the whole
thing is
a story it's like he jumps in and you
forget that you're watching a
presentation it's much more like you're
almost it feels like you're watching
like a documentary by a really good
knowledgeable source and he starts it
off with a personal connection which you
know sandy started her talk off with a
personal connection Nick starts his off
with a personal connection I think
there's something to learn there that
that personal connection is a really
great way to get the audience grounded
and to let them know that you are a
human who is not just gonna like lecture
to them you are also you know thinking
and you have problems you have
challenges and that's great
he has very few words on any of the
slides I mean it's it's like he even put
some technical diagrams up there to
illustrate how a nuclear power plants
work but it's not like they're full of
jargon or anything it's like there's
just there very understandable simple
pictures that you can you can take away
from and he does a couple things then in
the actual throughout the talk so one is
he explains a really complex process
which is nuclear power generation which
for most people in the audience who are
software engineers we didn't know much
about that topic probably so he kind of
walks through the basics of that and the
whole talk is only thirty minutes so
it's not like he has a ton time but he
makes it very digestible and
understandable and I think that's
something I've tried - I've noticed that
a lot of good speakers do and I try to
emulate myself is I make a really big
complex topic understandable and
digestible by anyone in any audience and
he does a good job with that finally
he's really polished in what he does
it's like he's not reading from a script
but it feels like he knows almost every
word that he's going to say I don't
think he says once and he doesn't look
thee is not like you know looking down
and reading notes the whole time um you
know kind of looking at it critically I
think he does maybe have a couple
moments where he has to go check his his
slide note speaker notes but it's not
like it's the whole time I sit there
reading so it feels very organic and
then finally he's bringing it all
together and making the whole thing into
a memorable story that's actually
applicable and again actionable so it's
great when people tell a story but like
you got to remember what's to take away
and I think Nick could
gotten up on stage and he could have
just said don't blame people when things
go wrong just fix the process but
instead of saying that saying in 30
different ways he just told one big
story that Illustrated exactly that
point and if you remember that story
you're gonna remember his point and it's
hard to forget that story once you watch
it it's just a really fascinating story
from engineering and reliability is it
so really some great takeaways from
those stories I'm gonna summarize it I
think you said it's very important that
you as a speaker you have a personal
connection to the topic because then you
also create a personal connection to the
audience they will care about you and
then they care about what you have to
say you have to think about what are the
takeaways for your your audience's daily
life as programmers if you if you have a
complex topic make it simple and
understandable put it in a nice story
and make sure that everything is very
polish that you Lou probably because of
practice you look like you're telling it
just to someone in a pub or in a plane
like that it's just this thing I tell
you rather than a memorized presentation
that actually also brings me through the
next stop a because one other thing you
said is you shouldn't have to mix too
much text on your slides and I was going
to ask you do you have any tips for
slide design so I guess not too much
text is one of them do you have any
others yeah one thing that I found a lot
of them speakers do is they have a
consistent payson of their slides so
what I mean by that is there's a general
rule of thumb that in business outlook
like in a business setting you probably
want to spend you want to think that
each slide will probably be about a
minute on average now that's not true in
necessarily in all contexts so for
example I've seen some speakers that
come up with for a 30 minute long
presentation they may have 200 slides
because they move really quickly it's
like each slide is a really quick little
you know thing that almost almost like
each slides a bullet point whereas other
speakers spend maybe two or three
minutes or more per slide so what you
want to do is think about like what is
my pacing going to be how often am I
going to be clicking through slides here
do I want it to be really fast or want
to be really slow don't be around that
meant for slide I found myself
personally I tend to hit around a minute
the slide but that's something that's a
lot of speakers I think don't think
about and then there's a lot of like I
don't know what I would call this like
sort of the mechanical stuff about
slides themselves so you want to use
large fonts you want to use few words
because the you know it gets hard to
read you want to also think about the
size of screen that the slides will be
projected on so for example if you're at
a meetup group it might just be a you
know small projector or a large TV even
at an office and there might be so you
might not be able to cram a lot of stuff
on there you may not want to put any
very small text whereas sometimes at
conferences they have a huge screen and
it'll be replicated across the room and
so you'll notice that sometimes speakers
will just put their Twitter handle very
small bottom every slide and it's okay
because it's blown up so big people can
find it or see it so you kind of want to
know the size that you're going to be on
if you can get it that's one of those
things if if you're accepted to a
conference you can always ask the
organizers about some other things have
good contrast and think about that color
contrast on slides so this is kind of
starting to get more we start to become
more aware of accessibility when it
comes to web development but it's still
something that has probably got a lot of
room for improvement in conference and
speaking sort of side of things and one
thing you can do there is think about
the large proportion of the population
that's colorblind or has some level of
colorblindness or maybe vision
impairments and things like that so
ideally the conference is doing some
kind of you know live transcription so
that there are subtitles you probably
talk to worry about that but if you can
subtitles it order sign language
depending on what they've got anyway
um but if you can think about your color
schemes and making it a good like
contrast of black and white or you know
yellow and dark blue so things stand out
against each other well I think that
covers some of the basic things that
come up about presentations that there's
sort of a whole discipline about
figuring that like writing a good slide
they're building good slides and
so I don't cover that in the book in a
ton of detail because I think there are
some good resources out there but I
linked out to some resources that are
good for for coming up with slides and
making sure they are very presentable
yeah I think the most important things
you said we're related to readability so
make sure to form this big and a
contrast is okay and also I really liked
your tip about pacing like how many
slides you want to have per minute and
is it sort of the same throughout the
entire talk that sort of relates to talk
delivery so that would be my next
question what are you tips for
delivering the talk so this pacing is
both related to slide design but also
related to delivery and also in the
talks that we looks at together you said
it's important that it's foolish and it
has this story like storytelling feeling
about it what are other tips you would
have about delivering this all a lot of
comes down to practice to be honest
because the more you practice the better
your delivery will get the more you
practice in front of a live audience the
better your delivery will get because
you'll react to how real people react to
what you're saying and so you'll start
to learn which parts to pause at which
parts to do to emphasize which parts to
maybe cut from the presentation so
that's by far the biggest tip is that
some other things that I like to think
about are one try not to read from your
slides if at all possible there's ways
you can do that by having your you could
have your presenter notes maybe show up
on your screen while the slides are
behind you this is something that a lot
of speakers maybe find hard to set up
and so they they don't do initially if
you if you don't need notes that's kind
of even better if you kind of know what
each slide is gonna be and then you are
able to sort of in your maybe you've
given the talk so many times you can
just hit those highlights without notes
that's great but a lot of people find
that having those notice is a good
backup plan in case they really get
flustered or lose track another thing
that I bet a lot of good speakers have
told me and that I agree with is to
memorize your very first sentence your
opening line because to be honest that
is once you get past that things kind of
roll downhill you've got a little
momentum so maybe you memorize your
first paragraph of what you're gonna say
just so that you you know you get on
stage those lights hit
and this is the first thing I say
because I've found a lot of first-time
speakers especially it's like once
you're actually up there everything
changes
the everything you practice and learned
is like thrown out the window because
it's a little scary when you've got you
know 100 people out an audience looking
at you for the first time so practice
that very first line but don't make the
whole thing like so rehearsed that you
are basically reading it make it feel at
least somewhat organic if you can get
audience participation throughout the
talk that is a really great way to kind
of make your talk about a little more is
it stands out it's a little more
interactive so that can be as simple as
asking a question maybe asking people
have you worked with react before raise
your hand and you'll get you know good
percentage of people will just get a
little the wake up a bit
once they they have to raise their hand
and think about a question that's
helpful you can also go further and do
kind of I've heard of speakers and scene
speakers who do more interactive almost
interactive sessions for their talks now
this is a little hard to pull off it can
depend on the venue but you can get
audience participation and talks you can
have people come up on stage with you if
you want to illustrate a point you could
tell they give the audience paper and
have them work on some little thing
again that's all kind of hard to pull
off and it just depends but it's a great
idea to get the audience involved in
some way
and then some other things to think
about are your first and last slide so
this pretty mechanical but one of the
things that you probably want to do is
have like a cover slide that'll sit up
there on the screen while you get set up
and while the you know the switchover
happens between speakers so that'll be
up there for maybe 5 or 10 minutes so
having something up there that's a good
introduction to what this talk is like
the title will talk maybe even you're
handling on social media so that people
can follow you or tweet along with it
and it's a good idea and then the final
slide as well you can either have like a
quick anybody got questions slide where
it's placeholder for questions or you
may tell people you know that I'll take
questions in the hallway afterwards or
here's my email or Twitter handle so you
can follow up with questions if you want
another thing that a lot of speakers try
to do that is tricky to do as well as
humor
and I've seen some speakers who are
really funny they they just kind of
naturally know what's what a good way to
to get a rise out of the audience's
without crossing line into controversy
but I've also seen a couple speakers who
cross the line into something that they
probably should have said on stage and
had to go back and apologize for it and
so I would just caution you to be very
mindful of any kind of humor humor just
in general it tends to but if you do try
to use it try to use positive humor
so maybe self deprecation is okay but
don't do it at the expense of making fun
of other people because you never know
who's in that audience who's going to
hear that or what they've been through
and so be very careful with anything
that's it's dark or edgy in your humor
so those are some things that that I've
heard and taken away from a lot of
speakers I've interviewed with theirs
again with presenting theirs there's a
lot of different topics and tips that
are out there another one that that
personally I adhere to is to try not to
get stuck standing right behind the
podium some speakers like that and that
that's okay but a lot of speakers you'll
find like to walk around a little on
stage and kind of use their hands be
very expressive be very engaging in
their their body language because you
have to remember just because you're on
stage it doesn't mean that that body
language communication doesn't happen so
a lot of I don't know what they say like
90% of communication is nonverbal or
something and that's true when you're on
stage as well so if you're not if you
don't look engage you're not moving
around you don't have like expressions
on your face the audience is gonna have
a really hard time reading you and
telling what they should be taking away
from this talk and what parts are
important so those are some highlights
and I'm sure there's plenty of other
things that I think you're throwing
about I kind of leave it there yeah that
was a lot so I'm gonna try and write
things on what you said so the final
thing is that is used body language try
to use the entire stage so people can
connect to you more easily memorize your
first few sentences so that you don't
have to worry about the beginning and
and it sort of rolls from there those
were tips I think you said were
generally applicable then you also said
some things are are good but hard to do
like audience participation it can be
really helpful to get feedback but it
can also probe that if people don't
reply and also you know of course if you
can do it if fits you it's very nice but
you have to make sure that it fits
because there might be cultural
differences and your humor might not
resonate with everyone and be sure to
make yourself the butt of the joke and
not other people because that might not
be all that funny to everyone so those I
think were some of the tips that you
said all very helpful and good to keep
in mind then there's one topic that I
would like to talk about before we close
of this episode we talked about it
briefly already and that are live demos
when we talked about it earlier you said
there they're really cool but they're
also sort of risky so let's look at the
positive side of it first what do you
think life coding adds to a talk that
just showing slides couldn't yeah so
there's a in the guy that kind of linked
to this this one talked where there's a
guy and see if I can find his name's
Andrew Sorenson and he does live
programming demos where he creates a
whole cup concert basically live so he
uses this this looping program in this
code to actually write music on the
stage it's amazing I mean you see that
and in he has a ten minute time slot and
he actually gets this whole like a mini
concert going in this program that he's
writing and it's really cool because you
can you see him live writing and
screwing up occasionally and fixing it
and it's inspiring I mean it makes you
as an audience member think oh this guy
I can do it on stage in ten minutes
surely I can do something you know
beautiful with my free time you know
what I want to go build something and I
think that that's that that inspiration
factor it's really high when you can do
it live for a lot of live demo speakers
what they're trying to illustrate is how
easy something is so maybe they're
they're using an open-source library
they really like or they built and
they're just showing this is how quick
it is to get your website up running
using this tool or to provision a
database using this tool or what have
you
and showing that you could do it live in
a few minutes
sort of shows the audience that this
isn't something that you need to be
afraid of it's not as scary as they
might have thought initially so that's
the plus side that's where I think live
coding does really well in those
contexts so the added value is I think
you said like giving inspiration moan
mainly that if people look at people
doing it actually they're like oh I
could do it because I saw all the steps
and there's no hidden magic that I don't
know about that's the added value right
yeah so then also you said it's risky
then what are the risks what did you
take on if you decide to do life coding
in a talk yeah well if you've been to a
few conferences you've probably seen
someone's life code it's unfortunately
it's very common and I remember one
young guy he was a first time conference
speaker he was going to try to give a
live demo of this tool and that he lost
the code something happened to get saved
and he didn't have his demo essentially
and he was really flustered it was very
difficult in fact a couple of the
audience members got up on stage with
him to help him out a little which was
really nice and because he was he was
really struggling and so first of all if
you do decide to go high-risk and do
something live know that the audience is
rooting for you so don't when it screws
up don't get up there and think to
yourself like oh gosh if I you know this
messes up I should just leave and never
do this again sort of take a step back
and remember that the audience wants you
to succeed because they they came to see
this thing happen and so you might even
get somebody in the audience who's going
to help you out or you may find that you
know there's a there's a silver lining
in it on the flipside you can do some
things to help mitigate the risk there
so a big thing is make sure you have
some kind of backup in case you're live
demo doesn't work so one of the things
that inevitably happens is you get to a
conference and the Wi-Fi goes down or
it's unbearably slow and so nobodies
live demos works this happens all the
time because we've got lots of people
accessing at the same time and for some
reason we can't figure out Wi-Fi so a
backup would be maybe having a video
that's embedded
into your presentation that doesn't
require the internet to run or having a
screen I like to use this program called
record it to record gifs live on my
computer and so I'll record gifs of all
the steps that I'm going to take live
baby before I actually go out there try
to do it live
and then obviously practicing a lot is a
big big part of this so I know I keep
that tip keep coming up but I think it's
really important and then finally the
last thing you can do is to sort of
coordinate with the organizers maybe the
day the conference starts or the morning
before your talk see if you can get and
try on stage a like live demo just to
see how it works with their equipment
just to make sure the audio-visual
people will maybe have it set up early
you can give it a shot just make sure
you know what you're getting into so
that's kind of some of the ways you can
you can devious get a bit but it's still
a tricky thing to do and tribute really
tricky thing to do yeah so you're saying
it's inherently risky but if you want to
go for it some tips could be to practice
it really well if it's possible to
practice it at the venue in the actual
room with equipment you're gonna use and
also have a video or some screenshots as
a backup that you can use if it fails
then you don't have to rely on getting
it to work you can just say okay
nevermind here's your video that would
be some tips that could make it like
less risky yeah and then weighing all of
that what is your final vote would you
say yes try it if it fits her story or
would you say no especially beginning
speakers better to to not take the risk
you know I say especially beginning
beginner speakers probably should
you know first taught you probably
shouldn't try this live demos now rules
are meant to be broken so I'm all for
people that employ it go for it anyway I
you know I I don't ever like to
discourage people from from something
entirely if so if a you know first-time
speaker came to me and she said you know
I am just super jazzed about this topic
and I think I could do a live demo I've
done this a hundred times I feel very
confident I would say you know I would
give her all the same tips but I'd say
go for it and so I wouldn't discourage
you
if you're just set on it but I would
also think about is there a good way to
give the same information without the
live demo is that the only way to get it
across but again everybody is different
and I think that's one thing I've taken
away from doing these interviews with
all these different speakers is
everybody's got their own method their
own style and that's okay that's great
in fact I think that's one of the fun
things about going to conferences is
getting to see all the different styles
that are out there and getting to
appreciate people who are great live
demos or great it making slides or great
it showing their their libraries they've
built and just comparing all these
different methods and ways to speak
actually I think that's a very nice way
to end the episode that yes there are
all these tips that we cover in this
episode and all the books and all the
videos you can see online but ultimately
there are different ways to do it and
part of the experience I think as a
speaker is also figuring out who you are
as a speaker and accepting that indeed
it is different for everyone and it
might be things that will not work for
anyone except for you and part of the
process is also figuring out what those
things are so I have asked everything I
wanted to ask and I do think that is a
great ending but if there's anything you
would like to add this would be the
moment for that no yeah I'm sure you'll
have the link to the speaking guide on
CFP lands so people can read more if
they want to get into that but we really
covered a good portion of it here today
so I just hope everybody I'm all for
more speaker just getting up on stage
and trying it so I hope it gets harder
and harder for me to get accepted
because there's so many great people
applying and I encourage everybody to
give it a shot at some point yeah that's
amazing thank you we'll definitely add a
link to your Twitter profile and you see
you feel and we will also add the links
to the two talks that you really like so
people can also look at those for
inspiration and with that I just like to
thank you for being on the show today
Carl yeah thanks fellate it was great
talking with you developers take your
marks it's time to upgrade your data
platform to inner systems iris it's time
to deliver complex mission-critical
applications in the fastest route
possible it's time to use any data from
any source it's time to embed analytics
and create interactive user interfaces
so what
waiting for choose your language choose
your tools choose your environment
collaborate build faster and deploy more
efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems comm slash tried to try
iris thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening